ANKIT SHARMA

Cost conscious and highly analytical Industrial Engineer with track record of optimizing quality and manufacturing process

CONTACTS





ankitsharma@nyu.edu

CORE COMPETENCIES

- Excellent interpersonal and communication skills in dealing with personnel, customers and external contractors
- Proven ability to apply mathematical concepts and interpret an extensive variety of technical instructions
- Demonstrated personal initiative and problem solving skills
- Exceptional communication, teamwork and influencing skills that foster a collaborative and continuousimprovement environment
- High energy level, adaptive and a strong team player with a good work ethic

KNOWLEDGE AND IT SKILLS

Software:

- Microsoft Office (Word, Excel, PowerPoint)
- Microsoft Visio
- AutoCAD
- Factory IO
- Connect IO
- Witness
- Minitab
- Tableau
- RSLogix (PLC Programming)
- FactoryTalk View

PROFILE STATEMENT

Creative and tenacious professional, armed with in-depth knowledge and highly successful experience in facilitating engineering process improvement initiatives, manufacturing, product development and management and business process analysis. Quality-focused Industrial Engineer with track record of designing efficient products, quality and profitability through keen data analysis and process design. Possess well developed ability to design, develop, test, and evaluate systems for managing industrial processes including human work factors, waste elimination, quality control, inventory control, logistics and material flow, cost analysis, automation and production coordination.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

New York University, Tandon School of Engineering, Brooklyn, NY Master of Science in Industrial Engineering

University of Mumbai, Rajiv Gandhi Institute of Technology, Mumbai, India Bachelor of Engineering in Instrumentation Engineering

Jun. 2014

May 2017

SKILLS AND EXPERTISE

- DMAIC Process Improvement(Six sigma)
- Lean Manufacturing
- Process Design and Simulation
- Operations Management
- IT Solution Implementation

- Statistical Process Control
- Vendor Selection and Negotiation
- Facility Layout Design
- Product Design and Fabrication
- Supply & Value Chain Management

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Nu-World Corporation, New Jersey, United States Industrial Engineer (6σ and Lean Expert)

Sept. 2017 - Present

- Designed and improved manufacturing processes for optimum efficiency and throughput
- Revised workorder scheduling method and trained the scheduling department on smart scheduling which resulted in 20% decrease in changeover time
- Prepared engineering CAD design and layout of a new \$2.5 million bulk manufacturing project
- Project Leader of 5S committee Trained managers on 5S techniques and led the committee to implement 7 5S projects in quality, warehouse, production and manufacturing departments
- Replaced comments on downtime issues with downtime codes for accurate data analysis
- Programmed and implemented "Quanto Analysis", a VBA program which reduced production
 data availability from two weeks to 8 hours and analysis time from 3 hours to 3 seconds,
 automating downtime, schedule attainment and line leader performance analysis
- Conducted multiple Lean Manufacturing training sessions for Line Leads which helped increase their average schedule attainment from 75% in December 2017 to 93% in August 2018
- Standardized production lines by developing operations sheets for specific products
- Proposed the redesign of the entire manufacturing facility based on Lean principles, prepared CAD draft and currently working on its implementation

Key Achievement

 27% increase in pieces per man hour, 20% increase in plant efficiency, \$2 million in labor savings over 2017, \$250k savings from downtime reduction

Programming Languages:

- Java
- SQL
- VBA
- XML, API
- R Programming
- LaTeX
- Ladder Logic
- CNC Programming

Concepts / Methods:

- DMAIC Process Improvement
- Kaizen (Continuous Improvement)
- Time and Motion Study
- Trend Analysis
- Fishbone Analysis
- FMEA
- Pareto Analysis
- Process Capability Analysis
- Value Stream Mapping
- Statistical Process Control
- Root Cause Analysis
- TPM
- 5S

Technical Consulting & Research Inc., Connecticut, United States Industrial Engineer Consultant Intern June. 2017 – Sept 2017

- Analyzed cyber security issues faced by merchants throughout US and brainstormed solutions
- Developed implementation procedures for industries for NIST compliance
- Worked with cyber security graduates and examined human factors related to cyber crime
- Combined lean principles like "poka-yoke" and waste reduction to create presentation for all 14 NIST security requirements for easy NIST implementation by industries

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS

- Lean Six Sigma Green Belt (IASSC and CSSC certified)
- Lean Management Professional
- Kaizen Certified

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Factory Automation using Factory IO and PLC Logic Factory Simulation using PLC Logic, Udemy.com

Fall 2016

- Simulated a factory floor via Connect IO, complete with conveyors, industrial sorters, sensors, buffers and elevators
- Linked Siemens PLCSIM software with Factory IO to simulate processes and control conveyors and sorters using input from sensors and PLC ladder logic

Lean Transformation at Chipotle Mexican Grill Lean Manufacturing, New York University

Fall 2016

- Prepared Value Stream Map and conducted Time & Motion study of the server to identify non value added activities
- Utilized knowledge of Kanban, 5S, SMED, JIT, TPM, and cross training to reorganize the workflow and reduce the cycle time below takt time without addition of extra manpower
- Performed statistical analysis on the data using I-MR charts to determine if data is under statistical control
- Found root cause of variations, suggested solutions & methods to ensure quality compliance and defect reduction

Detergent Plant Facility Design Facility Planning and Design, New York University

Fall 2016

- Designed detergent facility layout using AutoCAD by calculating footprint and clearance around equipments
- Calculated the total warehouse space required based on plant capacity and space for hazardous material storage
- Determined material handling equipment between work flow steps to facilitate material flow

EXTRACURRICULARS ACTIVITIES

- International Society of Automation Marketing Secretary & Industrial Coordinator
- Organized industrial visits for 100 students for professional industrial exposure with total funds of \$30k
- Volunteered for NGO "We the People Foundation" & conducted seminars on women empowerment